"Food for Hair Growth "
Androgenic or androgenetic
alopecia, also known as
male or female pattern hair loss,
is one of the most common
chronic problems seen by dermatologists.
Wait, so it’s called male pattern hair loss
and female pattern hair loss?
Yeah, in men they call it
male pattern hair loss,
and in women they call it
female pattern hair loss.
Okay. Either way, it is characterized
by progressive hair loss,
predominantly of the central scalp.
I’ve talked about
hair loss supplements.
I’ve talked about hair loss drugs.
What about foods for hair loss?
What role might diet play in
the treatment of hair loss?
Human experiments with fecal transplants
offer a clue to how powerful
our microbiome is, with reports
of improvements in hair loss
after a fecal slurry made from freshly
passed stools from a donor
was administered into another person’s
colon, and not just by a little.
A totally bald guy starts
growing back hair a few months
after a fecal transplant and
a little over a year later,
check it out, completely regrown.
The moral of the story is
not to drink brown smoothies,
but to keep your good gut bugs happy.
Population studies have
found that male pattern baldness
is associated with poor sleeping habits
and the consumption of meat and junk food;
whereas protective associations were found
for the consumption of raw
vegetables, fresh herbs,
as well as the frequent
consumption of soymilk.
Drinking soy beverages on a
weekly basis was associated
with 62 percent lower odds of
moderate to severe hair loss,
raising the possibility
that there may be
compounds in plants
that may be protective.
Complementary and alternative
medicine treatments
“boast the ability to
’cure’ hair loss ‘safely’
with ‘less side effects’
than conventional medicine.
However, it is important...to look
beyond the overarching claims
and marketing to critically
review the literature.”
For example, many studies
have little relevance
because the evidence was
obtained on shaved rodents.
Hey, let’s smear shaved
mice with bee venom.
And even when they do clinical
studies on actual people,
sometime there’s no placebo
control; so, you have no idea
if the food had anything to do with it.
But there has been a randomized
double-blind, placebo-controlled study
of compounds in hot peppers and soy,
showing significantly higher
promotion of hair growth.
Here are some before-and-after
pictures of both men and women.
Okay, but what kind of
doses were they using?
6 mg of capsaicin a day and
75 milligrams of isoflavones.
Okay, what does that
translate out to in real food?
You can get 6 mg of capsaicin
in just a quarter
of a fresh jalapeno pepper a day.
That sounds pretty doable.
And you can get 75 mg of isoflavones
eating ¾ of a cup of tempeh
or just straight soybeans.
Soy nuts are even
more concentrated,
dry roasted soybeans,
but given the formation of
advanced glycation end-products
in high fat/high protein foods at
high temperatures, I’d suggest
avoiding routinely eating roasted or
toasted nuts, seeds, or soy.
There’s also been a
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of pumpkin seed oil.
Where did they get that idea?
In 2009, a study out of South Korea
found that randomizing men
with BPH—enlarged prostate glands—
to just 320 mg of pumpkin seed oil
a day (that’s about 16th of a teaspoon,
so just a few drops a day)
improved urinary flow rates.
Urinary flow continued to kink off
and decline in the control group,
but those taking the equivalent
of just like eating two
single pumpkin seeds a day saw
a significant improvement.
That would seem to be
an anti-androgen effect,
so maybe it would help with hair loss.
It seems to work in mice
when used topically,
but what about in people
just eating pumpkin seeds.
It couldn’t hurt.
Sadly, we often throw away
pumpkin seeds, squash seeds,
or watermelon seeds, and
they actually have
a rich repertoire of nutrition.
But you don’t know if they
actually work for hair loss,
until you put it to the test.
In a study, 76 men with male
pattern baldness received
400 mg of pumpkin seed oil
a day hidden in capsules,
or they took capsules instead of
the placebo for a few months.
Again, that’s only like eating
two pumpkin seeds a day,
maybe two and a half pumpkin seeds.
They measured scalp hair growth
with all sorts of objective
and subjective measures, and...
after 24 weeks of treatment,
self-rated improvement
and satisfaction scores
in the actual pumpkin seed
oil group was higher,
and they objectively had more
hair, a 40 percent increase
in hair counts compared to only
10 percent in the placebo group.
Here are some representative
before-and-after shots
of the improvement in hair
coverage on two and a half
pumpkin seed’s worth of daily oil.
Show those pictures to blinded
investigators who don’t know
who’s in which group, and they
rate the placebo groups as
getting slightly worse over time
but the pumpkin seed oil group
getting significantly better.
In the pumpkin group, 95 percent
remained either unchanged or improved,
whereas in the control
group more than 90 percent
remained unchanged or worsened.
Given such a pronounced
effect might we be worried
about sexual side-effects?
They looked before and after at
an index of erectile dysfunction
and found no evidence
of adverse effects.